Guide to the Texas Western Swing Hall of Fame Collection
The Wittliff Collections
Texas Western Swing Hall of Fame Collection
1930-1999
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Dressen, Al
SWWC.045
8 Linear Feet
7 boxes
The collection includes photographs, costumes, posters, awards, and clippings featuring Hall of Fame members.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Al Dressen since 1991.
Historical Notes
The Texas Western Swing Hall of Fame was founded in Austin by Al Dressen in 1988. Inductions have taken place at the annual Texas Western Swing Hall of Fame show, held in Austin during the years 1988-1993, and in San Marcos from 1994 to the present, on the third weekend in May. The Hall of Fame's first inductee was Bob Wills, leader of the legendary swing band, Bob Wills & his Texas Playboys. Other members include such artists as Hank Thompson, Laura Lee McBride, The Sons of the Pioneers, Floyd Tilman, Eldon Shamblin, Hoyle Nix, and Asleep at the Wheel. The Hall of Fame also publishes a newsletter, Jamboree, which keeps its membership informed of special events and features music reviews.
Scope and Contents
Photographs, costumes, posters, awards, clippings dating from 1930s-1990s and featuring members of the Texas Western Swing Hall of Fame comprise the bulk of this collection. Items of note include Bob Wills' hat and a fiddle he reportedly played, and Laura Lee McBride's fringed leather costume.
Index Terms
Subjects
Musicians -- Texas; Country music
Document Types
Western swing (Music)
Subjects (Persons)
Wills, Bob, 1905-1975; Dressen, Al; McBride, Laura Lee; Thompson, Hank
Subjects (Corporations)
Light Crust Doughboys
- Texas Western Swing Hall of Fame
  - List of inductees (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Poster featuring Bob Wills, The Sons of the Pioneers, Laura Lee McBride, The Light Crust Doughboys, Cliff Bruner, Milton Brown and his Musical Brownies, and Smokey Montgomery
- Hall of Fame Artists
  - General Publicity Photos, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contents
    Al Dressen
    Tommy Duncan, Bob Wills, and Laura Lee McBride
    Bob Wills and Hoyle Nix
    Bob Wills and Laura Lee McBride
    Sons of the Pioneers
    Ted Daffan
    Texas Swing Pioneers (Johnny Gimble, Jerry Gimble, Smokey Montgomery, J.R. Chatwell), Fall 1980
    McKinney Sisters (Dean and Evelyn)
    Tiny Moore
    Billy Briggs
  - Jimmy Davis - Photo, bio, clippings (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Light Crust Doughboys - Photographs and postcard (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Light Crust Doughboys - Hall of Fame Induction Award, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Light Crust Doughboys - Cotton shirts embroidered with band name (1 blue, 1 white) (Box 7)
  - Laura Lee McBride - Photograph (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Laura Lee McBride - Hall of Fame Induction Award, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Laura Lee McBride - Leather vest, skirt, and wrist cuffs (Box 7)
  - Hank Thompson - Photograph (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hank Thompson - Billboard Award, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hank Thompson - Cash Box Award, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Hank Thompson - Cowboy Hat (Box 5)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Radio interview with Johnny Gimble about Bob Wills' sideman Eldon Shamblin, National Public Radio, August, 12, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Hall of Fame Induction Award, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Poster signed by band, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Fiddle reported to have been played by Wills (Box 4)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Cowboy hat worn by Wills (Box 6)
  - Bob Wills and his Texas Playboys - Blue Blazer worn by Wills (Box 7)